We, as today's דף *Daf* is ל"ט *Lamed Tet*, and we start
on the third line from the top, last word of the line.
So let's take a look. אתמר *Itmar*. So we had a debate
in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* whether about if the שוחט Shochet *shechting*
an animal for a non-Jew and the non-Jew is thinking to use
it for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *Avodah Zarah*, or A, do we
have to be concerned that the non-Jew is thinking about עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah*? And B, even if he is, would that
invalidate the קרבן korban? *Korban*? And רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* is concerned
about both of these issues, and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna
Kamma* and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* are not concerned, either
because we don't assume that he's thinking about עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah.
*Avodah Zarah*, or even if he is, it has no relevance, it
does not define the שחיטה shechitah, *Shechitah*. The only thing that defines
the שחיטה shechita *Shechitah* is the one who is being שוחט Shochet.
*shochet*. As the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, זה מחשב וזה עובד לא
אמרינן *Zeh mechashrev ve-zeh oved, lo aminan*. We don't say this one
is thinking and the other one is actually doing the עבודה avodah
*Avodah* so as a קרבן korban. *Korban* or the שחיטה Shechita *Shechitah*
here, that does not have any relevance. I should by the way
mention that our משנה mishna *Mishnah* says השוחט לעובד כוכבים *Hashochet l'oved
kochavim*, and then it says סתם stam מחשבת עובד כוכבים לעבודת כוכבים
*Stam machsheves oved kochavim l'avodas kochavim*, that you're שוחט Shochet. *shechting* for
an idolater, the standard, we are רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* saying the
thoughts of an idolater are always to idolatry. That's because our משנה
mishna, *Mishnah*, like our גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, like all is, you know,
has been censored so that it does not use, so that it
constantly refers to a non-Jew as עובד כוכבים *Oved Kochavim*, עכו"ם *Akum*.
That's why, you know, because the Jews were in the Middle Ages,
the apostates told the Church about all of the negative stuff in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about non-Jews, so in order to say that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was not talking about the contemporary non-Jews, we
went through a period of self-censorship where we changed every phrase of
גוי *Goy* or נכרי *Nochri*, which just means generic non-Jew, to say
עכו"ם *Akum*, to say like star worshiper, idolater, so we could say
that it was not referring to contemporary non-Jews. But that's not the
standard term, the original term in the text. So actually the original
term in the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* was השוחט לנכרי *Hashochet l'nochri*, just
a non-Jew, a נכרי *Nochri*, and the phrase סתם stam מחשבת נכרי
לעבודת כוכבים *Stam machsheves nochri l'avodas kochavim* that רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar's*
statement is the standard thoughts of a non-Jew are for עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah*. So you know, certainly in רבי אלעזר *Rabbi
Elazar's* eyes every non-Jew is an idolater. But it's an important point
here that the actual original phrase was נכרי *Nochri* as
just the standard non-Jew. So let's take a look now at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, three lines from the top, last word on the
line, אתמר *Itmar*. It was said, השוחט את הבהמה לזרוק דמה לעבודת
כוכבים *Hashochet es habeheimah l'izrok dama l'avodas kochavim*. So until now we're
talking about a different person is having the thought, the owner of
the cow, the non-Jew, and we have to also try to guess
what he's thinking. Now we're talking about that it's the שוחט Shochet
*shochet* himself who is having the thought, and we know exactly what
he's thinking. Okay, so let's take a look. Somebody is שוחט Shochet.
*shechting* a בהמה beheima *beheimah*, לזרוק דמה לעבודת כוכבים *l'izrok dama l'avodas
kochavim*. As you're שוחט Shochet *shechting* this בהמה *beheimah*, you're saying to
yourself, wow, when I get this blood I am going to use
this blood to put on the altar of Zeus. Okay, so you
have plans to use the blood in an idolatrous practice, but your
שחיטה shechting *shechitah* is not itself a שחיטה shechita *shechitah* for Zeus.
You're just שוחט Shochet? *shechting* it now for the meat. Okay, you're
not thinking about doing this as a, as a, what do you
call it? As a, oh my God, look so bizarre, the wireless
but we don't have the anyway, you're not planning on doing this
itself as a form of serving, of serving this idolatrous god, but
what you are planning is that, what do you call it? What
you are planning is to use the blood for that.
Isn't that the same thing?
Same thing as planning for the שחיטה shechita.
*shechitah* to do for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah*?
Well, a, no, the simple case is you bring your animal in
front of the idol and you slaughter it and this act of
slaughtering is itself one of the rituals of worship, right? Like slaughtering
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. But here, no, no,
no, you're slaughtering in the slaughterhouse, but you're saying I'm going to
collect the blood and then bring the blood to the temple of
Zeus and then do a זריקת הדם zrikas hadam *zrikas hadam* there.
Well, because the act of שחיטה shechita *shechitah* itself, that's the question,
do we consider the act of שחיטה shechita, *shechitah* itself an act
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah* if it was not being
done in the שחיטה shechting *shechitah* was not in the context of
serving? But he was planning on what he was going to use
the blood for in the future. Does that now redefine the שחיטה
shechita *shechitah* as an act of service? That's exactly the question. We
know if the שחיטה shechita *shechitah* was in front of the idol
and it was done in a ritual way, that would be an
act of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah*. When the blood is
being thrown, that's going to be an act of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah, *Avodah Zarah*. But the שחיטה shechitah. *shechitah* in the slaughterhouse for
the sake of getting the blood for throwing the blood, does that
make the שחיטה shchitah *shechitah* into an act of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah *Avodah Zarah*?
But wouldn't it be פיגול piggul. *pigul* if it was a כהן
kohen *Kohen*, wouldn't that be?
Well, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's* going to say. Do
we learn from the model of פיגול piggul. *pigul*? So that's exactly
the question. So let's take a look. Okay, so you're planning on,
you're שוחט shecht *shechting* it סתם *stam* for the meat, but you're
going to use the blood to sprinkle to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah,
*Avodah Zarah*, או להקטיר חלבה לעבודת כוכבים *o l'haktir chelba l'avodas kochavim*,
or to use the fat to offer up to עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah *Avodah Zarah*. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, and this
is even a Jew, you know, and we know exactly what you're
thinking and you're שוחט shocheit, *shechting* it and this is what. Does
your future plans impact the status of what you're doing right now?
רבי יוחנן אמר פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan amar psulah, the animal is פסול,
pasul, which means that it is considered to be slaughtered for עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah. something slaughtered or offered to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah.
is called זבחי מתים zivchei meitim and is forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah,
an offering to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah ריש לקיש אמר מותר, Reish
Lakish amar mutar, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no, you have עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah? plans but you haven't yet done an act of
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. and therefore the meat is okay. Now of
course they could have, if they were discussing this in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
they would have asked whether you are חייב chayav for worshipping עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah and have you done the violation and are you
חייב מיתה? chayav misa? But we're not now questioning whether you have
violated worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah and whether you're חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. We don't care right now about your personal obligation and transgression;
we care about whether you've affected the status of the meat. That's
our focus right now. Okay, but they are linked questions. So let's
take a look, potentially linked, you could maybe distinguish between them. But
anyway, right now we are concerned about the status of the meat.
So let's take a look what this is based on. רבי יוחנן
פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan psulah, so
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's invalid, מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה, machshavin me'avodah
l'avodah,
thoughts during one ritual act
can have significance from one עבודה avodah to another, your מחשבה machshavah
is significant, ואפינן חוץ מפנים, v'afinan chutz mipnim, and רש״י Rashi actually's
גרסא girsa or read of this is דאפינן חוץ מפנים, d'afinan chutz
mipnim, and or because we learn outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
from inside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, Now this is exactly what
רש״י Rashi says. This idea of doing one עבודה avodah, and thinking
about your future plans is exactly the model of פיגול. piggul. You
slaughter the animal, you plan to throw the blood at the wrong
time, you plan to eat the meat at the wrong time, or
you sprinkle the blood and you plan to burn the fat at
the wrong time or eat the meat at the wrong time. You're
doing one עבודה, avodah, you're planning for another; that is classic
פיגול. piggul Everybody knows that that's פיגול. piggul, The question is can
we use that model to tell me something, A when it's not
פיגול piggul and B when it's not a
קרבן? korban, Outside here we're not dealing with פיגול, piggul dealing about
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah and B we're also dealing with something that's
not a קרבן. korban So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. says yes, we
can use that model. We see that a thought during one of
these ritual acts, one of these עבודות, avodot, although here it's not
an עבודה, avodah has significance even when it's about a future עבודה
avodah and therefore the meat is invalid.
It also shows a non-כהן kohen. can do פיגול piggul then.
Right, but again it's the same way it's not in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash it's also can be a non-כהן. kohen, So in
theory the גמרא Gemara could have said that: אפינן חוץ מפנים, afinan
chutz mipnim, אפינן חולין מקדשים, afinan chullin mikodashim, אפינן זר מכהן. afinan
zar mikohen. But that's exactly the point. In the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash, we know it's a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. it's a קרבן,
korban it's a כהן, kohen but can we extract the idea of
doing one עבודה avodah and thinking of another, that it affects the
status to cases which have nothing to do with a קרבן korban
and a כהן kohen and so on?
Do we have פיגול piggul by non-כהנים? kohanim?
No, not on the במה.
bamah. What?
Because there's no פיגול piggul on the במה. bamah. Oh you have
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and oh my God I don't even remember
anymore whether you have פיגול piggul on a במה. bamah. Okay, anyway,
so not classically. במה's bamah a good question.
Okay, so that's רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש
אמר מותר, Reish Lakish amar mutar, it's permissible, אין מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה,
ein machshavin me'avodah l'avodah, מחשבה machshavah on one עבודה avodah does not
affect another, דלא גמינן חוץ מפנים, d'lo gaminan chutz mipnim, and we
do not learn outside from the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, Now there's
an interesting clear conceptual question which also might get to the core
issue of what I said about I assumed that you've done an
act of worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah, and you know and you
could have debated that, but also debating the status of the meat,
or
you could equally be debating whether you've done an act of worshipping
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, they just are happening to debate whether you've
affected the status of the meat. But you know in theory you
could say not necessarily. You could say worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah
I haven't done yet, I just have plans to worship עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah I slaughtered the cow for the meat, I have plans
to use the blood, I got plans for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah
We all have a lot of plans, you know, מענטש טראכט און
גאט לאכט. mentsch tracht un Gott lacht. So whatever, I've got plans,
okay, but I haven't worshipped עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, yet. But what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan could be saying is who said you haven't
worshipped עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah, But what we see from פיגול pigul
is that if you have certain plans about what to do right
as that can affect the status of the meat, so it's not
like you've necessarily done that act yet, but that could at least
say the meat is פיגול pigul when you're in the context of
doing this and planning for another step in what would normally be
a sacrificial process. So here too if you're doing שחיטה, shchitah? which
is normally a part of a sacrificial process even though it's outside
the מקדש, Mikdash, and you're planning of throwing the blood, that can
define the meat even though it's not yet עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
You could have said that and that actually gets to the heart
of a, so A that's possible, maybe you didn't do עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah. but you've just made the meat פסול, pasul, you know,
you've made the meat, you've given it that status because of when
you had your thought. That also gets to the heart of the
general question that I've asked you which is the following: when we
talk about כוונה, kavanah, is כוונה kavanah important because it redefines the
act or is כוונה kavanah important because it itself has the power
to do things? If
I... Does that redefine my act of שחיטה shchitah, *shechita* like Rivka
was saying? If you're now thinking about sprinkling the blood and you're
שוחט shochet, *shechting* now, the act you're doing right now is an
act of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. *avoda zara*. It's an act of
a form of serving the god because it's part of that process.
Okay, you've redefined your act right now. That's one thing you could
say. If that's true, then I'm also חייב chayav *chayiv* for עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah. *avoda zara*, I've worshipped עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avoda
zara* and I'm חייב chayav *chayiv*. Or do you say no, your
thought did not redefine your current act, but the thought has the
power to change the status of the meat when it comes at
this time. Do you understand the two different ways of thinking about
it? So is it the thought that is changing the status or
the thought is redefining the act? And that would also be the
question of whether according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe Yochanan* you've
actually worshipped עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avoda zara*. Take a look at
this little line at the end of this first תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafot*
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says that it's
about redefining the act. I'm not going to get into what bothers
תוספות Tosafot: *Tosafot*, but he says ועוד *va'od*, three lines before the
word אלא Ela, *ela*, the big new תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* אלא *ela*,
he says דהכא אפילו ידוע ודאי שלא יזרוק *Dehacha, afilu yaduah vaday
shelo yizrok*, even if we know that eventually you won't throw the
blood. You plan on throwing it, but we have a crystal ball
and we know you will never succeed in throwing the blood. And
you never do succeed in throwing the blood. Nevertheless חייב *chayiv*, דחשיב
עבודת כוכבים בשחיטה זו מה ששוחט על מנת לזרוק *dechashiv avodat kochavim
bishchita zo mah sheshochet almanat lizrok*. So it's not the fact that
you eventually throw the blood. Since that's your plan, what you're doing
now is considered an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara *avoda zara*.
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* very much says the מחשבה machshava. *machshava*, the
intent, redefines this act as an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara
*avoda zara*, and therefore you could have רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe
Yochanan* could have easily just have said you're חייב *chayiv* for worshipping
עבודה זרה avodah zarah *avoda zara*. But an alternate read is, no,
that's not what we learn from פיגול pigul, *piggul*. From פיגול pigul
*piggul* we learn your thought can affect the status of the meat,
but we're not learning to redefine the act. Okay, so that is
two different ways of thinking about what is behind רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan. *Rebbe Yochanan's* position. Let's take a look now.
How can you generalize something from קודשים *kodshim* to חולין Chullin. *chullin*?
Well, that is a good question and that, you know, and that's
never sort of spelled out. You're right. Presumably those issues...
okay, I'll get to that. Anyway, so that's the question about... so
that's the issue about what do you call it, about how can
you generalize it. So first of all, you have to ask why
by פיגול pigul *piggul* if you have thought about one thing does
it redefine the other? Right? Does the thought about, you know, during
שחיטה shchitah, *shechita* about the future how does that, how do we
interpret that? Is that because it now redefines the שחיטה shchitah *shechita*,
the current שחיטה shechita *shechita*, or is it because, you know, somehow
the power of כוונה kavanah *kavana*? But I agree either way, either
way you're right, either way whatever the model is, why should I
assume the same model is true in a different context? Right? If
it's true that כוונה *kavana* has a power by פיגול pigul, *piggul*,
whoever said כוונה *kavana* has an equal power by עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *avoda zara*. עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avoda zara* is very חמור
*chamur*. Right? Yes, but you don't know as the משנה mishna *Mishnah*
says, you don't know מחשבה machshava *machshava* has the same power בחוץ
*bachutz* as it does בפנים bifnim *bifnim*. Right? Maybe this is the
debate between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Reish Lakish*. Well right, but that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is going to say. But isn't that a debate here of the
תנאים *tanaim* of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*? So and don't—isn't the סתם
*stam* position not like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbe Eliezer*, that we
don't learn חוץ מפנים Chutz Mi-pnim? *chutz mipnim*? So what you're actually
saying is really what the חכמים *chachamim* say back to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbe Eliezer* in the משנה mishna? *Mishnah*. Why can you
just apply what we know about קודשים *kodshim* to outside of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beit Hamikdash*? And yeah you're right, but you
know the question is just as good as it was in the
משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. Whatever model you're using, whether it's the power of
כוונה *kavana* or whether it's redefining the act, the rules might be
different by פיגול pigul *piggul* than they are by עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *avoda zara*. Now if all רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe Yochanan*
is saying is I'm not trying to get you killed for worshipping
עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *avoda zara*, I'm just trying to say that
the meat is invalid, you've changed the status of the meat, then
it's a little bit more understandable. Because then it might be that
even though it's true these are different realms, but then it might
be true that if we're not asking about what constitutes a transgression,
certainly a transgression of פיגול pigul, *piggul*, a transgression of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah. *avoda zara* should be determined based on different factors, right?
But if we're asking like what type of things can you know
sort of change the status of the meat that you're slaughtering that
you're dealing with, there you see at least I think you can
see a little more commonality there that maybe doing things wrong in
a certain way, you know, will affect the status of the meat.
But you're right, even there you could say maybe not, maybe they're
very different types of problems. So it's a good question, but to
me it's a little toned down if we're just focusing on the
meat and not on the transgression. But you are right, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe Yochanan* is definitely a חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, yes.
This is a Jew sacrificing for an idol?
Yes, so no, for this case of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbe
Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* is a Jew planning
to worship עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avoda zara*. Okay? The Jew for
the non-Jew is the משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. Okay, so now let's see
where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes. Okay, and it says like
this, ואזדו לטעמייהו *ve'azdu leta'ameihu*, they go according to their reasoning, meaning
they had another debate that exactly paralleled this debate. אתמר *Itmar*, it
was taught, שחט shechts *shachat*... שחטה לשמה lishma, לזרוק דמה שלא לשמה.
lizrok dama shelo lishma. Now this is an easier debate because it's
all within the world of קרבנות. korbonos. A כהן kohen, שחט shachted
a בהמה for the sake of an עולה, olah, it's an עולה,
olah, but he says to himself when I get around to throwing
the blood I'm going to throw it לשם חטאת, leshem chatas, okay?
And so he's planning on doing a wrong the עבודה avodah with
the wrong intent in the future, but right now he has the
right intent, okay? And if he has that right intent in the
future, he'll either if it's a חטאת chatas he'll invalidate it, if
it's something else he'll make it not עולה לבעלים, olah leba'alim, so
does the plan for the future wrong intent, does it have an
impact right now? So let's take a look. Okay so רבי יוחנן
אמר פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan amar psulah,
it is invalid, we the fact what is future intent is has
an impact right now. ריש לקיש אמר כשרה, Reish Lakish amar kesheira,
it's kosher. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. אמר פסולה, it's invalid, מחשבין מעבודה
לעבודה, m'chashvin m'avodah l'avodah,
your thought from one עבודה avodah to a different עבודה avodah from
one עבודה avodah is relevant. How do we know that? וגמרינן ממחשבת
פיגול. v'gamrinan m'machsheves pigul. Again פיגול pigul is the paradigm. פיגול pigul?
is exactly you're doing one עבודה avodah. and you're planning on doing
the wrong thing in a different עבודה. avodah So רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says before you get to out of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash which is a much bigger חידוש chiddush as James pointed out,
you can even have can you use it as a model within
the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash, You're not dealing with פיגול, pigul you're
dealing with a different problem of intent, שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. Can
we learn from פיגול pigul. that a plan of doing שלא לשמה
shelo lishma at a future עבודה avodah should have relevance right now?
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says yes, I'm willing to learn from
the model of פיגול pigul to other forms of wrong מחשבה. machshavah
That's what he says. ריש לקיש אמר כשרה, Reish Lakish amar kesheira,
it's kosher, אין מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה, ein m'chashvin m'avodah l'avodah, from one
עבודה avodah to another your thought doesn't matter, ולא גמרינן ממחשבת פיגול
v'lo gamrinan m'machsheves pigul because we don't learn out from פיגול, pigul
פיגול Pigul is its own category, you can't apply it to anything.
So here you again really see again emphasizing James' point how big
of a חידוש chiddush, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is. Number one he
starts with פיגול, Pigul. he expands it thoughts that are not even
פיגול pigul related but are קרבן korban related, that itself is a
חידוש, and then he even takes it outside of קרבנות korbonos all
together and outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, all together. And
that's what the גמרא Gemara now says why we had to teach
both debates. So let's take a look.
וצריכא, u'tzricha, you need to tell me both debates. דאי אתמר בהא,
d'ei itmar b'ha, if it just told me in the one debate,
בהא קאמר ריש לקיש משום דחוץ מפנים לא ילפינן. b'ha ka'amar Reish
Lakish mishum d'chutz mipnim lo yalfinan. So the issue of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and out of the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-mikdash then we
would of course understand ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish How can you learn
issues of עבודה זרה avodah zarah. from thoughts of the בית המקדש,
Beis Ha-mikdash, from פיגול? pigul, They're completely unrelated. So there we understand
why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish rejects רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. דחוץ מפנים
לא ילפינן. d'chutz mipnim lo yalfinan. אבל פנים פנים, aval pnim pnim,
two different types of קרבן Korban. thoughts, פיגול pigul, and שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma, אימא מודי ליה לרבי יוחנן, eima modi lei l'Rabbi Yochanan,
maybe he would agree to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you could
learn one from the other. ואי אתמר בהא, v'ei itmar b'ha, and
if you just said the debate about שלא לשמה shelo lishma thoughts,
so then I would have said the opposite. בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן,
b'ha ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan, that's where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is prepared
to say we learn from the model of פיגול. pigul We take
פיגול pigul, and we apply it to שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. אבל
בהא, aval b'ha, but when it comes to שחיטה shechita for עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah it's not dealing with a קרבן Korban at all
as James said it's completely different
category, אימא מודי ליה לריש לקיש, eima modi lei l'Reish Lakish, maybe
he would agree to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that your thoughts are
irrelevant. צריכא, tzricha, so you need to tell me both debates. So
again by the way notice that for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, the
underlying common denominator here is not to say whether you've violated, but
whether your thoughts can invalidate. Okay so again it might very well
be he's not prepared to say you worshiped עבודה זרה, avodah zarah
but what he learns from פיגול is when you are doing one
עבודה avodah and your thoughts about another and if those thoughts were
done in the future or if they were done now, if it
would invalidate, so then the thoughts about the future also invalidate right
now. That's what he says. And James of course says okay but
why should we assume that that's equally true in all cases? And
especially because the whole phrase of עבודה לעבודה, avodah l'avodah, the whole
concept of עבודה Avoda is only a concept by קרבנות. korbonos. Now
it might be very well true that the only reason he's willing
to apply it by עבודה זרה
avoda zara as עבודה זרה avoda zara.
exactly is its own form of sacrificial ritual. Correct, so it's not
קדשים, kodoshim, it's not a כהן, kohen, it's not whatever, but maybe
looking through the lens of עבודה זרה avoda zara this is a
form of sacrifice. It's also has some sense of being a sacrifice.
Right, so it wouldn't necessarily say let's say for example I'm writing
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and I'm writing this שם השם Shem
Hashem לשמה, but I'm planning that when I get to the next
שם השם Shem Hashem I'm going to write it שלא לשמה. shelo
lishma. Right, presumably רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say that has nothing
to do with anything, it's completely unrelated.
Exactly. Not to salt or not to... exactly. But here we are
talking about something which is a other form of sacrificial ritual, just
an idolatrous sacrificial ritual. So there at least we're willing to make
the comparison, right? And that's why I think again that it's much
better if we're not trying to hang you
for transgressing, you wouldn't be hanged, but we don't want to kill
you for transgressing, but we're just trying to determine the status of
the actual meat. So then we would say when we are within
things which are considered forms of sacrificial ritual, whether they're in the
temple or whether they're out of the temple. whatever, we look at
intention plays a role and plays a role in determining status. And
even intention about the future can determine how we look at this
act, you know, how it defines the status of what you're doing
right now. Which is very different than תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says
no, now it means that you're worshipping עבודה זרה, avoda zara, which
I think is a much bigger jump than a question of defining
just the status of the meat, okay?
So if you were baking bread with the intent...
exactly, right, none of that is ever part of the discussion. So
it's very much within a world that you can use the phrase
עבודה Avoda and מעבודה לעבודה, Me-avoda Le-avoda, from שחיטה shechita to זריקה.
Zrika. Right? So it's still very much following that same pattern that
you get in the עבודה Avoda of a קרבן. korban All right,
so let's now continue. Okay, מתיב רב ששת, Masiv Rav Sheshet, or
ששת Sheshet asked. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, קל וחומר דברים.
Kal Vachomer Devarim.
So this is our משנה, Mishnah right, where there's also a debate
of do you learn חוץ Chutz מפנים? So let's take a look.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says to רב אליעזר, Rav Eliezer, I'll make
a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer why the thought of the non-Jew should
not affect the meat. This is a case where again the person
other than the שוחט shochet. is having the thoughts. Okay, ומה במקום
שמחשבה פוסלת במוקדשין, U-mah Bemakom She-machshava Poseles Be-mukdashin, what do we find
where thought does invalidate by קרבנות? Korbanot? אין הכל הולך אלא אחר
העובד, Ein Ha-kol Holeich Ela Achar Ha-oved, the only person's whose thoughts
matter are the one during the worship, doing the worship, meaning the
שוחט. shochet. So if that's true, even by קרבנות Korbanot it's only
the thought of the שוחט. shochet מקום שאין מחשבה פוסלת בחולין, Makom
She-ein Machshava Poseles Be-chullin, meaning in non-sacrifices, אינו דין שלא יהא הכל
הולך אלא אחר השוחט? Eino Din She-lo Yehei Ha-kol Holeich Ela Achar
Ha-shochet?
How much more so should it only go by the שוחט shochet.
and not by the non-Jew? And we know that of course רב
אליעזר'ס Rav Eliezer's response is number one, by קרבנות Korbanot he believes
the owner's thoughts do matter. And number two, he's prepared to learn
from קרבן korban to other things. Fine. But we are now going
to focus in on the assumption of רב יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's question,
which is that thoughts matter in קרבנות Korbanot and they don't matter
in חולין. Chullin. And we're going to say what does that mean?
So let's take a look. מאי אין מחשבה פוסלת בחולין? Mai Ein
Machshava Poseles Be-chullin? What does רב יוסף Rav Yosef mean when he
says thoughts don't invalidate by non-sanctified meat? אילימא דלא פסלה כלל, Ileima
De-lo Pasla Kelal, thoughts never invalidate? אלא זובח לעבודה זרה דמיתסרא היכי
משכחת לה? Ela Zoveach Le-avodah Zarah De-mitasra Heichie Mashkachat Lah?
So when would you ever find that slaughtering an animal, a cow
for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, the meat would be forbidden? The whole
way in which you know we have a category
called תקרובת עבודה זרה, Tikreves Avodah Zarah, something that is offered to
idolatry, to an idol, which is forbidden in benefit. So obviously thoughts
do invalidate when you do a real worshipping of עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. So you can't mean thoughts never invalidate. So what do you
mean? אלא
פשיטא מעבודה לעבודה. Ela Peshita Me-avoda Le-avoda. Now if you... before we
get to what the גמרא Gemara thinks it means, the answer really
does seem to be obvious. Yes, there are cases where in non-קרבנות
Korbanot thoughts invalidate, like a thought for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah, But
the range of thoughts that are a problem are much smaller. The
only thought that's a problem outside the בית המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash is
a thought for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. In the בית המקדש, Beis
Ha-mikdash. there's a lot more thoughts that are a problem. If you
slaughtered it with a thought to be זורק את הדם Zorek Es
Ha-dam at the wrong time, to eat it at the wrong time,
פיגול thoughts are a problem, שלא לשמה Shelo Lishma is a problem,
שלא לשם בעלים Shelo Leshem Ba'alim is a problem. There are a
million other thoughts that invalidate in the בית המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash, than
out of the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-mikdash, So that I would say,
interestingly the גמרא Gemara ignores that, but that I would say is
the simple meaning of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. In the בית המקדש,
Beis Ha-mikdash thoughts are always invalidating. Out of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash it's very rare for a thought to invalidate. But the גמרא
Gemara doesn't take that tack. The גמרא Gemara says what does he
mean that out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it doesn't invalidate?
So let's take a look. אלא, so here's what he means. אלא
פשיטא מעבודה
לעבודה. Ela Peshita Me-avoda Le-avoda. He means thoughts don't invalidate from one
עבודה Avoda. to another עבודה. Avoda והכי קאמר, Ve-hachi Ka'amar, this is
what he's saying to רב אליעזר. Rav Eliezer. ומה במקום שמחשבה פוסלת
במוקדשין מעבודה לעבודה, U-mah Bemakom She-machshava Poseles Be-mukdashin Me-avoda Le-avoda,
we know by קרבנות Korbanot thoughts invalidate from one עבודה Avoda, to
another, meaning פיגול. And even though thoughts have the power to invalidate
to another עבודה, Avoda, very powerful in קדשים, Kodshim, nevertheless אין הכל
הולך אלא
אחר העובד, Ein Ha-kol Holeich Ela Achar Ha-oved, the only person's whose
thoughts matter is the one doing the עבודה, Avoda, the שוחט. shochet
So even though thoughts have that power that they can... that even
when they're applied to another עבודה, Avoda, they invalidate. Nevertheless, it's only
the thoughts of the שוחט that matter. מקום שאין מחשבה פוסלת בחולין
מעבודה לעבודה, Makom She-ein Machshava Poseles Be-chullin Me-avoda Le-avoda,
places where thoughts do not have an ability to impact when they're
about another עבודה, Avoda like in non-קרבנות, Korbanot, when thoughts about another
עבודה avoda. are irrelevant, אלא באותה עבודה, Ela Be-osa Avoda, they only
invalidate when they're in this act itself, אינו דין שלא יהא הכל
הולך אלא אחר השוחט? Eino Din She-lo Yehei Ha-kol Holeich Ela Achar
Ha-shochet? How much more so should it only go by the שוחט?
מעבודה לעבודה, Me-avoda Le-avoda, what do you mean בחולין?
Be-chullin? This case about רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא? Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada?
You're שחיטה shechitah, it with a plan to be זורק את הדם
Zorek Es Ha-dam to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah So the גמרא Gemara
is choosing to read, one minute, רב יוסף Rav Yosef who's saying
thoughts are much more powerful by קרבנות Korbanot than by חולין. chulin,
rather than what I again think is the פשט, pshat, which is
just that there are so many different types of invalidating thoughts. It's
saying, no, no, no, what it means is thoughts by קרבנות, korbanot,
you can have a thought about a different עבודה. avoda That's your
פיגול thought. You're doing שחיטה shechitah and you're thinking about זריקה. zerika.
Whereas by חולין, chulin. thoughts are less powerful because if it only
becomes a שחיטה לעבודה זרה shechita l'avoda zara when you're doing it
right now with the intent that this is לעבודה זרה. l'avoda zara.
Your plan about the future עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, that's irrelevant by
חולין. chulin, So the way the גמרא Gemara is now reading this
is he is explicitly or implicitly, you know, rejecting רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan He is saying that by חולין, right, your thoughts about another
עבודה to do the דם לעבודה זרה dam l'avoda zara is irrelevant
right now if you're doing, you know, in terms of your שחיטה.
shechitah, So the way so that is a total contradiction of רבי
יוחנן the way the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read it. Okay
is that clear? Yes? You look like you have a quizzical face.
You got it? Okay.
So basically they're saying עבודה לעבודה, avoda l'avoda, so you know,
they're reading it into רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi right, it's a complete,
I don't get the question at all. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi could
easily be read to be talking about other issues about thoughts being
more powerful in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but it's choosing to
read that what he's saying is that in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash עבודה לעבודה avoda l'avoda matters, but out of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash thoughts are not so powerful, their עבודה לעבודה avoda l'avoda
does not have power. And particularly in terms of עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah.
Well right, that's the whole point.
No, no, but I'm saying that's the only place thoughts even begin
to matter out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
is עבודה לעבודה avoda l'avoda as we were saying before, which is
exactly why you can use that framework.
I understand, but that's at least ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, still
talks in that framework but rejects its implications. Okay, so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara, says.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: פנים קשיא לריש לקיש. Pnim
kasha l'Reish Lakish. The fact that he says I admit in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash the way we're reading it, עבודה לעבודה avoda
l'avoda works, that's a question to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who said
that it's only by פיגול, it's not in all areas in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash חוץ then when he says out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash עבודה לעבודה avoda l'avoda does not work, קשיא
לרבי יוחנן. kasha l'Rebbi Yochanan. That contradicts רבי יוחנן who says out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it does work, even out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it works. So let's take a look
at what the גמרא's Gemara answer is: בשלמא פנים לריש לקיש לא
קשיא. Bishlama pnim l'Reish Lakish lo kasha. The implication that in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash we always do עבודה לעבודה, avoda l'avoda, always
invalidates and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said only by פיגול, that's not
a problem. Why not? הא מקמי דשמיה מרבי יוחנן הא לבתר דשמיה
מרבי יוחנן. Ha mikmi deshama l'Rebbi Yochanan ha l'basar deshama l'Rebbi Yochanan.
In one case it was before he heard it from רבי יוחנן
the other after he heard it from רבי יוחנן. What does that
mean? So רש"י Rashi has two explanations both of which are bizarre.
One explanation is oh, well that's before רבי יוחנן taught it because
רבי יוחנן remember although he's always arguing with ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. actually started as his student. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying it was before he heard this משנה Mishnah from
רבי יוחנן, meaning basically saying before he learned this משנה, mishnah. he
assumed that even in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash עבודה לעבודה avoda
l'avoda was not an issue. Once he learned the משנה, he realized
oh based on this read of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi, whatever it's
clear that in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. עבודה לעבודה avoda l'avoda
is always a problem, which is very bizarre, which means we're assuming
that ריש לקיש number one, you know, formulated his opinions without knowing
a משנה and that they were actually recorded. And number two, we're
also assuming that he reversed himself even though we have no indication
that he reversed himself. Even תוספות: Tosafot הא מקמי דשמיה מרבי יוחנן.
Ha mikmi deshama l'Rebbi Yochanan. תוספות is תימה מאי תירץ הוא זה
שתירץ דאמר ריש לקיש קודם שלמד המשנה. temah mai teretz hu zeh
she-tiretz d'amar Reish Lakish kodem she-lamad hamishna. Okay, oh well that was
his opinion before he learned this משנה. So since when does anybody
formulate an opinion about anything before you've learned the משנה? They would
do that all the time. Well okay, nowadays, but hopefully since when
would we think the אמוראים Amoraim especially if you think about the
way in which in an oral tradition they used to learn, which
is first you memorize all the משניות mishnayot and then you start
thinking about them and having an opinion? And number two, why would
we not why would we have retained it and not have reversed
it if he had reversed himself? So that is a very weak
answer, a very strange answer to ריש לקיש. Oh yeah, that was
before he knew about the משנה. Alright, so let's see what
it has to say was a question even?
That the way the גמרא Gemara is reading רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi is saying in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
מחשבה למחשבה machshava l'machshava is a problem, and that sounds like it's
always a problem, not just by פיגול מחשבה למחשבה machshava l'machshava is
a problem but בפנים in all cases in the בית המקדש.
But I mean as we said, he's focusing on פיגול, it wasn't
necessarily, you could have said a million things and you could have
said it's not what רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi, was talking about anyway,
but the way the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read רבי יוסי,
Rebbi Yossi it's a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
that's ריש לקיש. אלא חוץ קשיא לרבי יוחנן, Ela chutz kasha l'Rebbi
Yochanan, this is the more obvious problem the way the גמרא's Gemara.
reading it. It's reading רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi to say that out
of the בית המקדש מחשבה עבודה לעבודה machshava avoda l'avoda has no
relevance, isn't that exactly what רבי יוחנן said that having a thought
about a future עבודה זרה Avoda Zara is relevant? So אלא חוץ
קשיא לרבי יוחנן הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. ela chutz kasha
l'Rebbi Yochanan hu mosiv lah v'hu mifarek lah. So רב ששת Rav
Sheshet asked this question and he gave the answer בארבע עבודות. b'arba
avodot. We're talking about only about the four עבודות, avodot, meaning that
we are about to see but I'll just tell you before, I
mean it's not even explicit גמרא, Gemara that the idea that if
you do an act on the קרבן for עבודה זרה it makes
the קרבן a תקרובת עבודה זרה tikrovat avoda zara is only if
you do what- is if you do שחיטה shechitah *shechita* or זריקה
zrika *zerika*, not if you do קבלה *kabala* or הולכה *holacha*, those
are the other two עבודות *avodot*. Okay, so only based on the
פסוק *pasuk* it says זבחי מתים *zivchei meitim*, the things that are
slaughtered to עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, and by the דם *dam* I'm
trying to remember how we learn that out, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* quotes
a פסוק *pasuk*, oh, בל אסיך נסכיהם מדם *bal asich niskeihem midam*.
Okay, a פסוק *pasuk* in תהלים *Tehillim* which emphasizes the blood. That's
where that act is considered that it's been offered to עבודה זרה
*avoda zara*. But if you just catch the blood or transport it,
right, you can understand that those are much seen as much more
secondary, much less as a direct act of worship, much more as
sort of like part of the process but not the actual worship
itself, so that there you do not actually define the animal as
being an offering to עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. So now how's that
going to help? Does this have to do with like השתחויה *hishtachavaya*
and all that? You could be חייב *chayyav* for עבודה זרה *avoda
zara*, but the question is again we're not focusing on when you've
transgressed, we're focusing, yes, you could be חייב *chayyav*, that's considered one
of the עבודות *avodot* for this for the בעל *Baal* or for
Zeus or whatever, you're חייב *chayyav*, but has that made it considered
like you've offered up the animal and that defines the status of
the animal? So we always have to distinguish between what constitutes an
act of worship at for you and a transgression and what constitutes
the animal's status in terms of having been offered. Is this what
we were thinking about those two in the future? No, no, even
at the time, even if as you're catching the blood, right, right,
I'm thinking this should be a catching of blood for Zeus, right,
so if this is a normal way Zeus is worshipped, I actually
have חייב *chayyav*
for עבודה זרה *avoda zara* because
I caught the blood for Zeus, but I have not defined the
animal as an offering to Zeus yet because it has not been
like the שחיטה shechitah *shechita* is done to the whole animal, okay,
the דם *dam* on the מזבח *mizbeach* maybe represents the whole animal.
Actually תוספות *Tosafot* says based on a later גמרא *Gemara* we're going
to see today that even when you sprinkle the blood, the only
thing that you אוסר *osser*, you make forbidden, is the blood. You
don't define the status of the whole animal.
So that only when the animal is shechted for עבודה זרה *avoda
zara*, the whole animal is considered an offering and it's forbidden.
If the blood is sprinkled,
the blood is an offering and the blood is forbidden. But if
the blood is caught or the blood is transported, I might have
worshipped עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, but I have not made the blood
or the animal into an offering because I haven't offered it yet,
right, I've done a ritual with it, but I haven't offered it
yet. Do you see the difference? Okay, yeah. But if you're shechting
it and thinking about throwing the blood then it would אוסר *osser*
the animal? So that's what we're going to discuss. Okay, yes, so
if you שוחט *shecht* and think about throwing the blood, you're doing
an act and an act which is the problematic act and a
thought on the problematic act. But if you let's say do things
about קבלה *kabala* and הולכה *holacha*, that's where it would not have
an effect and that's what we're exactly about to say. Is that
because these two עבודות *avodot* are lesser in the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash*? No, all four are in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, but
these two are in the פסוקים *pesukim* about עבודה זרה *avoda zara*
and as I said these two are about giving the thing as
an offering whereas קבלה *kabala* and הולכה *holacha* are not actually about
making it into an offering. They're really saying that it's you know
the עבודה זרה *avoda zara* models
pattern after the one in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* so there
should
really be no difference? Right, but we don't, we learn from specific
פסוקים *pesukim* that these are the two that have effect, let's say.
So let's take a look.
Okay and also, yeah, fine, let's take a look. To me, I
would have had a problem saying that if you're doing a קבלה
*kabala* for עבודה זרה *avoda zara* you're חייב *chayyav*. I'm glad, I
wouldn't have either until I read this גמרא *Gemara*, so let's take
a look. Okay, so you are חייב *chayyav* for עבודה זרה *avoda
zara*, the question is whether you affect the status of the meat.
Okay, so let's take a look. והכי קאמר *ve-hachi ka-amar*, this is
how to read it. ומה במקום שמחשבה פוסלת במוקדשים בארבע עבודות *u-mah
be-makom she-machshava poselet be-mukdashim be-arba avodot*, when it comes to קרבנות *korbanot*,
your thoughts are relevant in all of the four עבודות *avodot*, שחיטה
*shechita*, קבלה *kabala*, הולכה *holacha*, זריקה zrikah *zerika*. אינו כל הולך אלא
אחר העובד *eino kol holech ela achar ha-oved* and there so even
though your thoughts are relevant in many more categories, it only goes
by the one doing the worship. מקום שאין מחשבה פוסלת בחולין אלא
בשתי עבודות *makom she-ein machshava poselet be-chullin ela be-shtei avodot* when you
deal with non-קרבנות *korbanot*, thoughts only matter in two places, שחיטה *shechita*
and קבלה *kabala*, or שחיטה *shechita* and זריקה *zerika*, or שחיטה *shechita*
and planning for זריקה *zerika*, but anyway only two things are relevant
by non-קרבנות *korbanot* for עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, אינו דין שלא יהיה
כל הולך אלא אחר השוחט *eino din she-lo yehei kol holech ela
achar ha-shochet*, how much more so should it only go by the
שוחט *shochet* and not by the owner. So again what we're now
doing is we're totally re-reading, we're going back to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi *Rabbi Yosi*, we're saying no, no, there's no need to read
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* as talking about עבודה לעבודה *avoda la-avoda*, right,
and that led to our whole problem that we read him like
he was saying עבודה לעבודה *avoda la-avoda* is a problem in the
בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, is not a problem out of the בית
המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. Forget that, he's not talking about עבודה לעבודה *avoda
la-avoda*. He's saying מחשבה *machshava* is more problematic in the בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash*. Why? Because in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* מחשבה *machshava*
can impact the status on any four עבודות *avodot*. Whereas out of
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, when you have a thought of עבודה
זרה *avoda zara*, that only impacts the status at שחיטה *shechita* and
at זריקה *zerika* and not at the middle עבודה *avoda*. So forget
עבודה לעבודה *avoda la-avoda*, that's not what רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* is
talking about, he's talking about the four עבודות *avodot* versus the two
עבודות *avodot*. And here we do have this very fascinating thing that
you could be doing these rituals to עבודה זרה *avoda zara* and
being transgressing עבודה זרה *avoda zara* but not affecting the status of
the meat, okay, because those two things do not exactly coincide. So
those two things do not always come exactly in line. Is it
also starting and ending like we had in the last משנה? What?
Except of the beginning and the סוף sof like we had in
the last משנה that when something starts, when something ends. Oh, יש
צד מתחילה ועד סוף. yesh tzad mit'chila v'ad sof. Why is that
relevant? Because שחיטה's at the beginning and זריקה's at the end. Oh,
it is a process, yeah, but there they are definitely considered to
be, you don't have the same debate because there they are considered
to be distinct and separate sets, so as opposed to שחיטה, which
is sort of one continuous process. I wanted to mention one final
thing which רש"י Rashi does mention before we move on, which is
the question about, so we mentioned שחיטה לעבודה זרה shechita l'avodah zarah,
and the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam, לעבודה זרה. l'avodah zarah But there
actually is something else which is much more intuitive that we would
have identified as what it means to make the thing an offering
to עבודה זרה and to make it forbidden. What if I told
you if you make something an offering to עבודה זרה it becomes
forbidden, what image is the first thing that pops up into your
mind? Putting it on the altar. Putting it on the altar, right?
So that would be like burning the fat. So basically, and by
the way, if you ever go to Greece or and Rome and
you look at these ancient sites about these temples to the gods,
the basic way an offering that non-Jews gave things to them on
the altar wasn't just slaughtering animals. They would actually put jewelry and
art and different types of actual things. We discussed this once before,
they just found this temple, was it a Buddhist temple or where
was it, in India, that had billions of dollars' worth of art
and gold and whatever in its treasury about things that have been
given over the years and placed on the
temple. So anyway, how about that? That makes it a תקרובת עבודה
זרה. tikroves avodah zarah. And the answer is yes, it makes what
was put on the altar a תקרובת עבודה זרה, tikroves avodah zarah,
but it doesn't make the whole animal into an עבודה זרה. So
if you put the fat on the altar, the fat now is
forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, but the meat is not. And תוספות by
the way says that the same is true about the blood. That
even when we talk about your מחשבה about the blood, the blood
becomes an offering, which is because you would think at least there
the blood represents the whole animal, but based on the later גמרא
the תוספות says no, even there just the blood becomes the offering
and not the rest of the animal. So it is true by
the way that one of the things that should be added here
is the הקטרה, haktara, the offering and the burning on the altar,
but that does not at least affect the status of the whole
animal the same way the שחיטה does.
So the only way to make the whole animal forbidden is the
שחיטה לשם עבודה זרה. shechita l'shem avodah zarah.
Right. Now from רש"י Rashi it sounds like also זריקת הדם, zrikas
hadam but based on a later גמרא תוספות modifies that. So he
says the זריקת הדם for תוספות is just like the הקטר חלבים,
hecter chalavim, it only affects the status of the thing actually being
placed on the altar. Right. When you're doing this.
So is that what we say in the end, that really that
I'd have
to see, I mean who פוסק, paskens, who's מנבל menabel of the
specificity details?
But whereas for anything you do it's still you could be killed
but the meat is okay.
And we're going to continue discuss that tomorrow as well. So let's
keep on
going. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, Tanya k'vassay d'Rabbi Yochanan, השוחט את הבהמה
לזרוק דמה לעבודת כוכבים ולהקטיר חלבה לעבודת כוכבים, Hashocheit es hab'heimah lizrok
damah l'avodah kochavim ul'haktir chalavah l'avodah kochavim, exactly רבי יוחנן's case. You
שוחט it for the sake of doing זריקה לעבודה זרה, zrika l'avodah
zarah, notice also burning the fat לעבודה זרה, l'avodah zarah. had it
mentioned that before? So especially in the what we said just a
minute ago about the ארבע עבודות. four avodot. But the act you're
doing now is the שחיטה act. הרי אלו זבחי מתים, Harei elu
zivchei meisim, that does make the meat forbidden in benefit. By the
way I should add something as well. Remember what we said before,
is it now that your כוונה invalidates or is it that now
the action becomes redefined as a different action? Given that if you
actually succeeded in what you were planning, burning the fat לעבודה זרה,
l'avodah zarah, you would not have affected the status of the meat.
If you actually burned the fat לעבודה זרה, l'avodah zarah, you only
would have forbidden the fat, not the meat. And now we're saying
because that's your plan you actually have invalidated the meat, it sounds
like we have now redefined your act as a form of worship
and therefore the meat is forbidden. So that is this is an
interesting hint into that question about is it just the thought being
powerful or is it the act redefining the act?
It really doesn't make much sense though, if I actually succeed I'm
חייב in less and when I only
plan on it I'm חייב in, it's forbidden.
Because what you've done now is you've done a שחיטה לעבודה זרה,
l'avodah zarah, whereas in the other case you would just have done
a הקטרה לעבודה זרה. haktara l'avodah zarah. That is exactly what you
get by redefining the act rather than by focusing on the thought.
That's exactly the difference. שחטה ואחר כך חישב עליה. Shachata v'achar kishiv
aleha.
Now how about if you shechted it without saying anything? You were
שוחט, you shechted it, and then afterwards you said, oh this is
such great fat. I'm going to now take this to my altar
by Zeus. Okay, after the שחיטה. You're a good Jewish שוחט, but
afterwards you had a declaration that what you're planning on doing with
the fat or the blood. Okay, so the question is, סתם a
thought in a vacuum doesn't have any relevance if it's not in
the context of שחיטה or זריקה etc. But can we say that
your articulated thought now makes us go back and assume or question
what you were thinking when you actually did the שחיטה? That's the
question. Okay, so שחט ואחר חישב, shachat v'achar chishev, he slaughtered and
then you had your thought, you articulated your thought. זה היה מעשה
בקיסרי, zeh hayah ma'aseh b'Kesari, this was a case in Caesarea, so
interesting, it was a real case! Okay, there was, you know, it
was rampant in Israel, at the, you know, עבודה זרה was
rampant in Israel, at the, you know, and a lot of Jews,
especially you go to some of these temples, you know, and they
have the sun god there and all these types of things on
the mosaic. So we like to think everybody was so פרום, frum,
but no, you know, especially in that period of time there were
a lot of people that the influence, the, what's the word? Syncretism?
Syncretism? How do you pronounce it? Syncretism. Anyway, you know, the sort
of adopting of a lot of those outside practices, you know, found
their ways into, into, you know, sort of amongst some Jews, certainly.
So here was a guy, he שחט shecht it and then he
decided he was going to use the meat for... Well, we have
to assume before that we know מחשבה is being said, otherwise how
are we going to know?
Well, that's also true. At least in this case it was said.
זה היה מעשה בקיסרי, zeh hayah ma'aseh b'Kesari, so this happened in
Caesarea. ולא אמרו בו לא איסור ולא היתר. v'lo amru bo lo
issur v'lo hetter. They weren't able to have a clear ruling of
whether the meat was forbidden or permissible. So אמר רב חסדא,
Amar
Rav
Chisda, we're going to say, לא אמרו בו איסור משום כבודן של
רבנן. lo amru bo issur mishum k'vodan shel rabbanan. They didn't say
it was forbidden to show respect to the rabbis' position. The rabbis
in the משנה say, right, that if, that if somebody else is
doing the thinking, I'm sorry, forget that. The rabbis in the משנה
implicitly say that we don't assume the thought of a non-Jew is
for עבודה זרה, right? Only רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer assumes the thought
of a non-Jew is for עבודה זרה. The rabbis say we don't
סתם assume the thought of a non-Jew is for
עבודה זרה. So here
too, although this guy articulated his thoughts later, we're not going to
assume that at the time of שחיטה, we're basically going to give
everybody the benefit of the doubt. And therefore, unless we know exactly
that he was thinking about עבודה זרה at the time of שחיטה,
we're not going to assume it. So that, in order to show
respect to that position, we did not rule that it was forbidden.
לא היתר, lo hetter, but we didn't rule it was permissible, משום
כבודו של רבי אליעזר, mishum k'vodo shel Rabbi Eliezer, because normally רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer at least by a non-Jew, is concerned he's thinking
about עבודה זרה. So presumably here too by רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
a Jew who later expresses his desire for עבודה זרה will be
concerned that he's thinking about עבודה זרה as well. So we're basically
saying the rabbis are generally willing to give people the benefit of
the doubt and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is generally willing to suspect
people. So therefore in this case, it's not exactly the same, it's
not a non-Jew, it's a Jew who later articulated his thoughts, but
the rabbis will give him the benefit of the doubt from the
time of שחיטה
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer will not.
And therefore because
we didn't want to rule in that debate, so
we said the meat was not... we didn't say it was
מותר, muttar,
we didn't say it was אסור.
assur.
So in essence, they would be because of worry over the כבוד
kavod of the rabbis, they were paralyzed. Well, you know, what we
see today all the time. They didn't say yes, they didn't say
no, because they don't want to פסקן pasken against this rabbi. So
they won't say anything. Right. והם יעמדו. v'hem ya'amdu. Yeah, that's an
interesting point. No, but the point is respect for their ruling. Meaning
you're right, it's not necessarily respect for the person. The rabbis and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer were dead at probably at that time, but
right, out of deference to their position, our hands are tied. We
can't פסקן. pasken.
That's a very,
that's a very nice critique. I totally hear that. Meaning, you know,
yes, the responsibility of a פוסק posek is to make a decision,
not to say well, you know, it's a מחלוקת גדולה machlokes gedolah
and who am I to פסקן pasken and therefore we're always going
to be מחמיר. machmir. Right, especially nowadays. Right. That's a very point,
point very well taken. An absolute paralysis. Right. No, but the good
point is, is that the way it's being articulated is is that
they didn't פסקן pasken not
because they themselves
couldn't come to a conclusion, because they didn't want to be forced
to choose between the two positions of these two important figures.
Right. I hear.
Especially since משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, because we can't say that you
can
eat it and then you can't
eat it. Right. But anyway, so the point is very well taken.
Let's take a look because the גמרא continues. This is not the
only read of what happened, although it will be in similar lines.
So let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא says ממאי, mimai,
how do you know the positions of the rabbis and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer, would translate to this case? Because the rabbis and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, were debating the case of a non-Jew. דילמא עד
כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם, dilma ad kan lo ka'amri rabbanan hatam,
maybe I could argue both this is more lenient and I could
argue it's more strict. Maybe the rabbis only said by the non-Jew
case we're not concerned about his thought, אלא דלא שמעינן דחשב, ella
d'lo shamainan d'chashiv, we never thought that,
we never heard that... heard him articulate an עבודה זרה intent. So
אבל הכא, aval hacha, here by the Jew case, דשמעינן דחשיב, deshuminan
dechashiv, we heard him articulate his intent. It’s true it was later,
but we actually heard him say his plans for עבודה זרה. הוכיח
סופו על תחילתו, hochiach sofo al techilato, I'll say what he said
later reveals to us what his earlier thoughts were and that therefore
we should assume that at the time of שחיטה this was also
his intent. So this case might be worse than the case of
the non-Jew. There it was a non-Jew, fine, but here we actually
know the guy was planning עבודה זרה at least a later time.
אינמי, inami, or I'll say the opposite, that this is a better
case. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר התם, ad kan lo ka’amar
Rabbi Eliezer hasam, by there Rabbi Eliezer said we suspect the non-Jew,
אלא גבי עובדי כוכבים, ela gabei ovdei kochavim, because he was a
non-Jew, דסתמא מחשבת עובדי כוכבים לעבודה זרה, destama machshevet ovdei kochavim la'avoda
zara, we assume the thoughts of a non-Jew are always about idolatry.
So Rabbi Eliezer, it's maybe not a skeptical approach to human nature
in general, maybe it's just a skeptical approach
to non-Jews and their thoughts. Okay, for non-Jews he's going to suspect
them, or suspicious I should say, not skeptical. אבל ישראל, aval Yisrael,
but by a Jew who we normally assume is going to be
פרום, frum, even if we see later he has intents of עבודה
זרה, הוכיח סופו על תחילתו לא אמרינן, hochiach sofo al techilato lo
amrinan, we're not going to say that what he does later should
make me suspect what he was thinking earlier. So it's not necessarily
that the Rabbis always never suspect somebody and Rabbi Eliezer always suspects.
Maybe not, maybe Rabbi Eliezer has a thing about non-Jews and maybe
the Rabbis they're willing to suspect if they have evidence but you
need to start with a certain amount of evidence. So you have
no idea how the Rabbis and Rabbi Eliezer would translate into this
case. This case is different on two prongs: on the one hand
it's a Jew and on the other hand it's there is some
real evidence. After the שחיטה he articulated his intent. So you can't
say that that was what to use Rivka's very articulate very specific
very good phrase, this is what paralyzed them. So, אלא אמר רב
שיזבי, ela amar Rav Shizbi,
so here Rav Shizbi says you're right, that can't have been what
was leading to that problem. Here is why they were not able
to rule. לא אמרו בו היתר משום כבודו דרבי שמעון בן גמליאל.
lo amru bo heter mishum kvodo deRabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. They really
they wanted to say that it's forbidden, but they were not prepared,
I'm sorry, they wanted to say it was permissible because you did
not know the thought at the time, but they weren't prepared to
say it was permissible because of respect to Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel's
position that led them to say maybe we have to worry about
the past based on what we know in the present. So now
we are going to look for a different Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel
having nothing to do with שחיטה and עבודה זרה, but Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel who articulates this idea that when somebody says something now,
it makes us suspicious about what they were thinking and planning earlier.
So out of respect to that position they were not prepared to
say the meat was permissible. היי רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, hai Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel, which Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel is it that says
this idea of essentially הוכיח סופו על תחילתו? hochiach sofo al techilato?
That's the phrase. His end is evidence about his beginning. What happens
later is to give evidence about what was going on earlier. So
which Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel? אילימא רבי שמעון בן גמליאל דגיטין, ilimah
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel deGittin, maybe it's the one in גיטין. Gittin.
What's the case in גיטין? Gittin? דתנן, detnan, הבריי habari who said
כתבו גט לאשתי, kitvu get le'ishti, so if a healthy person says
to witnesses, write a גט get for my wife, רצה לשחק בה,
ratza lesachek bah, we can we have to be concerned that he's
maybe playing with her and he's not serious. Meaning what? That in
order to make a to appoint somebody as an agent to write
a גט, get, you say כתבו גט לאשתי, kitvu get le'ishti, but
if you want them to deliver the גט, get, you have to
say
כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי kitvu utnu get le'ishti or else we would
just assume you're just indicating making them an agent for the writing,
not for the גט. get. What we do say is in some
cases the context is so clear you want to give a גט
get that we assume you meant תנו. tnu. A guy is on
his deathbed, a guy's being taken out and being is going on
a faraway trip where it was a lot of danger, going into
the army or being taken out for an execution or whatever, there
we assume that when he says write a גט get he means
write and give. He's afraid he's going to die, his wife will
be a יבמה, yevama, so it'll make problems with her having to
do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with the brother-in-law, or maybe he's
and in those cases we assume that when he says write means
write and give because it's clear he's afraid he's going to die.
But this says no, if he's healthy and you don't have any
of those special cases, so maybe he's just like playing with her,
taunting her, saying haha, I have a גט, get, I'm not giving
it to you, or that's a literal translation of לשחק. lesachek. רש"י
Rashi tries to tone down the word לשחק lesachek to mean like
the wife is begging him for a גט get because she's concerned
that she's going to become a יבמה yevama and he's doing it
to like to quiet her, to make her feel happy but he
really is not planning on giving it to her. So at least
in רש"י it's not as bad as taunting, but it's still misleading.
But anyway the point is unless it's a if it's not a
special case, we have to assume the word write a גט get
just means write it and doesn't mean write it and deliver. So
that's the first statement. Now we're not yet where it's relevant for
us. ומעשה בברי, uma'aseh bevari, there was a story with a healthy
person who said כתבו גט לאשתי, kitvu get le'ishti, write a גט
get for my
wife, ועלה לגג ונפל ומת, ve'ala legag venafal vemet, he went up
to a roof and he fell and died. he died, and there's
a question about did he commit suicide? Okay, and if he committed
suicide, maybe we should understand that when he said "write a גט,"
get, he really meant "give the גט." get. Now we see, no,
and they wrote it and they gave it. They wrote it and
they gave it. And the question was, were they, have they been,
were they appointed agents to give it? Do we read his statement
"write a גט" get to mean "write and give"? Do we see
it as an appointing of agency for giving? Okay, do we say
that in the end, if he committed suicide, and again, why would
he rather his wife be divorced than widowed? Because of the יבמה
yevama situation. So if we see that he committed suicide, now maybe
we should go back and say he really did mean "give it,"
and therefore when they gave it, they really were his agents.
Does it make a difference when he committed suicide?
Like right then or three weeks later? Yes, well, some of that
would be brought in as well. So let's take a look, okay?
ועלה לראש הגג ונפל ומת. Veala lerosh hagag venafal vames. אמר רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, אם מעצמו נפל הרי זה גט, im
meiatzmo nafal harei zeh get, if he threw himself off the roof,
then it's a גט. get. Okay, now again, the question is like
how soon after? Fine, we can discuss that, that's not our topic
right now. ואם הרוח דחתו, Veim haruach dechaso, if he was pushed
off by the wind, if it was an accident, אינו גט, eino
get, it's
not. Okay, ואוינא בה מעשה לסתור, Vaavinan ba meisah lister, this contradicts.
A minute ago you said it's not "write it" doesn't mean "give
it," and here you said sometimes it does mean "give it." So
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Chisorei mechasra vehachi kateni, words are missing or
there's an implicit statement being made here, and here's what it's really
saying: אם הוכיח סופו על תחילתו, Im hochiach sofo al techilaso, if
in the end the end reveals the beginning, so we see that
even though he was healthy, based on later events, we understand that
he was concerned he was going to die. And then הרי זה
גט, harei zeh get, then we do understand that he appointed people
as agents to deliver
it. ומעשה נמי בברי, Umaiseh nami bebari, there was a story שאמר
כתבו גט לאשתי, sheamar kisvu get lishti, write a גט get for
my wife, ועלה לראש הגג ונפל ומת, veala lerosh hagag venafal vames,
he went up to a roof and he fell down and he
died. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, אם
מעצמו נפל הרי זה גט, im meiatzmo nafal harei zeh get, if
he threw himself off the roof, it is a גט, get, then
it's clear that he had plans of suicide. ואם הרוח דחתו אינו
גט, veim haruach dechaso eino get, if it's the wind, it's no.
So anyway, what do you see? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says that if we see what a person does in
the future, it makes us reinterpret what was going on in the
past. If we see he committed suicide, we're going to assume he
had plans of suicide. So therefore, we should say that if a
person says he's going to throw the blood לעבודה זרה, lavodah zarah,
we should say that at the time of שחיטה, he had the
plans to throw the blood לעבודה זרה, lavodah zarah, and the שחיטה
becomes invalid. No, so the גמרא says no. דילמא שאני התם דקאמר
כתבו. Dilma shani hasam deka’amar kisvu. There, once he committed suicide, we
say, "Oh, now I understand why he was telling those people to
write a גט." get. There was some actual thing that occurred earlier
that I can now reinterpret in light of this thing. And now
that כתבו kisvu can be an indication, a signal of his intention
to commit suicide. Whereas here, the guy is just a שוחט. There's
nothing different about what he did that indicates, that could even in
hindsight indicate a plan of עבודה זרה. Okay, so yes, we will
reinterpret, we will reflect if there was now when we look back,
we can see that that thing was a signal of his intention.
But we don't have that signal in our case of שחיטה, so
it should not be relevant. So the גמרא says, "All right, let's
try again." אלא אמר רבינא, Ella amar Ravina, so רבינא Ravina says,
משום כבודו דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל דהכא, mishum kvodo deRabban Shimon ben
Gamliel dehacha, the following רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
okay, in בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, דתניא, datanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braita: הכותב נכסיו לאחרים והיו בהן עבדים, Hakosev nechasav leacherein vehayu
bahen avadim, somebody gave over again presumably because he's on his deathbed
all of his property to somebody else and included in his property
were slaves. ואמר הלה אי אפשי בהן, Veamar halah i efshi bahen,
and the recipient says, "I don't want them," right? Because you know,
slaves is a lot of responsibility. So אם היה רבו שני כהן,
im hayah rabo sheni kohen, if the recipient was a כהן, kohen,
so if they're owned by a כהן, kohen. now they can eat
תרומה. terumah.
So the question is, and but this recipient says, "I don't want
them," do we assume are they owned by the recipient or not?
So the first ruling is, הרי אלו אוכלין בתרומה. harei elu ochlin
beterumah. They are owned by the כהן. His statement that he doesn't
want them doesn't matter.
We'll see why in a minute.
Did he actually take possession? We will see why in a minute.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, כיון שאמר הלה אי אפשי
בהן, keivan sheamar halah i efshi bahen, if he says, "I don't
want them," כבר זכו בהן יורשין, kevar zachu bahen yorshin, then it
shows that he never received them, and if he never received them,
so therefore the heirs of the donor receive them. They were, the
gift was never transferred and they pass on to the heirs of
the donor. Okay, so now what are we talking about? ואוינא בה,
Vaavinan ba, we asked on this: לתנא קמא אפילו עומד וצווח? letana
kama afilu omed vetzoaveach? Are you telling me according to the first
opinion this guy is standing and yelling, "No, I don't want the
gift, keep your gift to yourself," blah blah blah, and we're still
saying he gets the gift? Since when can somebody be forced to
get a gift that they don't want? אמר רבה ואיתימא רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbah ve’isayma Rabbi Yochanan, בצווח מעיקרא, betzoaveach me’ikara, if the guy
has been yelling from the very beginning, from the moment this person
has written out his gift, you know, his deathbed bequest, דכולי עלמא
לא פליגי דלא קנה, dechulei alma lo peligi delo kanah, everybody would
not disagree, everybody would agree that he did not take possession of
it. Right? He's always articulated that he doesn't want it. You don't
force a possession, a gift on somebody. בשותק. Beshotek. זכין לאדם שלא
בפניו. Zachin leadam shelo bifanav. Yes, but that is, that's normally that's
when it's a זכות. zechut. But if he's if he's expressed that
he doesn't want it, we would not call it a זכות. zechut.
Right. Okay. So בשותק ובסוף צווח beshotek u-besof tzavach if the person
by silence he received the gift, he took the... let's say it
was written in a שטר shtar and that transferred ownership and he
took it, he said thank you very much. And then he came
back yesterday and he said tomorrow... and he says you know what
I've been thinking about it and I realize I would rather not
have the slaves, I can't deal with the slaves. So okay, too
bad, you've already taken possession of it. כולי עלמא לא פליגי דקנה,
kulei alma lo peligi de-kana, everybody would agree that you've already taken
possession and you own it. So כי פליגי ki peligi what's the
debate? שזיכו לו על ידי אחר, she-zichu lo al yedei acher, there
you go, exactly Risto's case. Somebody else took the שטר shtar for
you. ושתק, veshatak, now you were present but you were not exactly
totally focusing on what was happening. Right? The guy didn't hand you
the שטר, shtar, he handed somebody else the שטר shtar to be
to take possession for you. So you were silent at that moment,
ובסוף צווח, u-besof tzavach, and then you know when you then you
started complaining. תנא קמא סבר Tanna Kamma savar מדשתק, mi-de-shatak, since you
were silent initially, קנהו, kanahu, you took possession. והאי דקצווח ve-hai de-ka-tzavach
and now that you're yelling, מהדר קהדר ביה, mahadar ka-hadar bei, now
you're reversing yourself, but at the moment which was critical you actually
took possession. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar
and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, הוכיח
סופו על תחילתו. hochiah sofo al techilato. We're going to say the
fact that you're yelling now shows that you never desired. דהא דלא
צווח מעיקרא, de-ha de-lo tzavach mei-ikara, so why didn't you yell at
the very beginning? סבר savar because you thought, כי לא אתי לידי
אמאי אצווח, ki lo atei liyadi amai etzvach, I haven't yet taken
possession of it, some other guy took the שטר shtar for you.
I won't complain yet, when they want to ask me to really
take possession, then I'll tell them that I don't like this whole
thing. So okay, now again it's not exactly clear because you know
if legally you took possession, what does it matter whether you have
or don't have the שטר? shtar? But the point still being that
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is more willing to
look at the current at the current situation and suspect or interpret
the past even if it's not so clear, whereas the תנא קמא
says no, we'll assume that what we're seeing now just occurred right
now. So since רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and
there there was not by the way an earlier signal about your
future intent like there was in the case about כתבו גט. kitvu
get. So we see that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is worried is takes a position about questioning the past or
interpreting the past through the lens of the present. And therefore in
the case where you had expressed after שחיטה that you were going
to throw the blood לעבודה זרה, l'avodah zarah, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would say I have to be concerned that
that was your intent at the moment of שחיטה and therefore you
cannot eat the meat. Let's just wrap up and get to the
משנה. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
הלכה כרבי יוסי, halacha k'Rabbi Yosi, we rule like רבי יוסי that
the thought of a non-owner is not relevant. Micha was asking yesterday,
what about if the person is a part-owner? According to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer actually that is going to be exactly discussed right now
in this גמרא. Let's take a look. הנהו טייעי, hanu tayei, there
were certain types of Arab traders, דאתו לציקוניא, de-atu l'Tzikunya, they came
to a place called Tzikunya. יהבו דכרי לטבחי ישראל, yehavu dakhrei l'tavchei
Yisrael, they gave their rams to Jewish שוחטים. shochtim. They were going
to use the fat of the rams to as for for עבודה
זרה, okay, but they they wanted it שחט shechting properly, so they
gave it to the Jewish שוחט. So here's a case, a Jewish
שוחט for an animal of a non-Jew. The non-Jew is planning at
least offering the fat לעבודה זרה. l'avodah zarah. Okay. So אמרו להו
amru lehu and they said to the Jews, דמא ותרבא לדידן, dama
ve-tarba l'didan, give us the blood and the fat, we're going to
use it for עבודה זרה. משכא ובישרא לדידכו, maskha u-bisra l'didkhu, you
can keep the skin and the meat. Pretty nice deal for the
Jews, right? Now one does wonder whatever happened about לפני עור? lifnei
iver? That's an interesting question which the גמרא doesn't get into. You
know, maybe you could say well they didn't say what they were
going to use the fat for, that's their business, it's their fat
anyway, I'm just שחט shechting it for myself, I'm going to get
the meat. Whatever it was, that was the case. So לפני עור
lifnei iver we're not concerned about, but does the intent of the
non-Jewish owner for עבודה זרה affect the status of the meat? So
שלח רב טובי בר רב מתנא לקמיה דרב יוסף, shalah Rav Tuvi
bar Rav Matna l'kammei d'Rav Yosef, the question was sent to רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. כי האי גוונא מאי, ki hai gavna mai, what's
the story, is the meat's status affected? שלח ליה shalah leh he
sent to him, הכי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, hakhi amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel, this is what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says in
the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יוסי, halacha k'Rabbi Yosi, we
rule like רבי יוסי that the thought of the owner is irrelevant.
The only thing we care about is the thought of the שוחט.
So the owners are planning for עבודה זרה, does not affect the
status of the meat. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לרב
אשי. amar leh Rav Aha berei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Ashi. So רב
אחא Rav Aha says to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that the thought of the
owner does matter, how much does the person have to be the
owner? Now רש״י Rashi says we're taking for granted that if the
person is a partial a real partial owner, his thoughts would invalidate
even if the other owner doesn't want it to be לעבודה זרה.
l'avodah zarah. The fact that he's a partial owner according to רבי
אליעזר that the thoughts of the owner matter, that's enough to affect
the whole status. But the question is what about if he's if
he's how how partial will his you know is it still relevant?
So let's take a look. What if it's an if it's if
you and I are... no... me and somebody else... me and Christopher...
own it and I'm שחט shecht it and he's thinking עבודה זרה.
No no no but that's the way around. So let's just look
at that we're already over time. So יהבי זוזי yahvei zuzai לטבח
ישראל ltavach Yisrael this עבודה זרה gives a non-Jew a buck or
five bucks and says I want a pound of the meat after
you שחט it. So now he's an owner of a pound of
the meat. Is he enough of an owner that his thoughts matter?
מאי? mai? What's his story? So אמר ליה חזינן amar lei chazinan
we've see. אי אלמא הוא ee alma hu if this non-Jew is
a strong person meaning he can force the Jew to give him
the meat even if the Jew doesn't want to because he wants
to buy it, so דלא מצי מדחי ליה delo matzi madchei lei
he has no way of pushing him off, אסור assur it's forbidden
because then he really has become a part owner in the meat
because the Jew's going to have to give him a part of
it. ואי לאו ve'ee lav and if he's not a strong person,
so אמר ליה amar lei so the שוחט can say to him,
רישך וטורא reishach vetura here's your head here's a mountain, which means
go bang your head on a mountain, okay,
which means he can basically tell to him it's very nice you
want to buy the meat I can always refuse. And since I
can always refuse, even if I don't refuse, the fact that I
could refuse means you were never a partner in the cow and
therefore your thoughts are not relevant. So real partnership is relevant for
רבי אליעזר quasi this type of partnership if it's not real partnership
would not be relevant and here.